[Music]
there's only one thing which I want to
mention more in a very uh you know very
very high level I don't want to get into
the proofs and other things the guys who
did the course last year actually had a
uh guest lecture from somebody who works
in this field and who was able to talk
about another technique which is gaining
a lot of popularity recently uh so he
talked about that in in in gory detail
in fact he did some proofs from one of
the papers that they wrote and so on so
forth uh but unfortunately I don't have
the guest lecturer here this time and
it's also I mean just I introduce you
the ideas to you and then if you want
you can read up on those later right uh
but in some sense whatever we have done
so far gives you all the tools that you
need you know it gives you the basic
tools for you to understand more complex
algorithms and so on so forth that's
that's the whole idea for me to do this
and if you actually look at the book
right the textbook um they almost in
passing mention all of these algorithms
right mean they have like one paragraph
saying oh this is how you do UCB and
this is how you do they don't talk about
Medan elimination at all uh this is how
you do something else which I'll talk
about in the next class called reinforce
right they mentioned these things in
passing and then they say oh we'll build
on some of these ideas as and when
required for the full reinforcement
learning problem right so in some sense
the the book treats Bandits as something
that you is a necessary evil that you
need to know about on your way to
learning about the full ARL problem
right given the focus of the book that's
a valid way of treating Bandit problems
uh but in fact it Bandits itself is a
very very rich large literature and it's
very active area of research for a lot
of reinforcement learning people that's
one of the reasons I actually covered uh
bandits in a little more depth than I
used to do uh maybe a couple of years
ago right so a couple of years ago I did
banditss in like one
class right all of
Bandits anyway so one thing which I want
to talk about
was Thompson sampling which is gaining a
lot of traction now okay uh so it's more
descriptively you could call it
posterior sampling depending on which
literature you're reading some some
people call it posterior sampling some
people call it Thompson sampling so the
basic idea is the following right so I'm
trying to solve a bandit problem right
and we know that if you know the the
parameters of the Bandit if I knew all
the Q Stars right I can solve it very
easily right so how what do I
do take the highest right so what I'm
going to do when I do this kind of
Thompson sampling approach uh is to uh
take a somewhat a basian way of looking
at these things right I'm going to say
that okay I'm solving this unknown
problem I'm solving this unknown problem
but I'm going to make some assumption
about the parameters of this unknown
problem right so essentially the
Assumption I'm making here is about the
Q Stars I'm going to make an assumption
that the true Q stars come from some
distribution right I'll start with some
guess for this the True Q stars come
from some
distribution right so if my if my uh if
I know that my uh rewards are limited
between 0 and one right like many of the
cases we being assuming rewards are
limited between 0 and one so what would
be an appropriate assumption for this
qar distribution
beta
distribution so people remember beta
distribution the guys who are in ml yes
the guys who are in ml at least should
remember the beta distribution so the
beta distribution is is a distribution
that is limited to 01 right and it can
take all kinds of weird
forms uh right and um so this is
typically a prior that prior
distribution that you assume uh whenever
you
have you you're trying to find
parameters of a uh uh distribution where
the parameters limited between 0 and one
okay so the beta distribution is a very
popular prior that is used like that I
make some kind of an assumption let us
say that I don't know anything about the
underlying uh problem right then what
will I
assume uniform right you can assume a
uniform distribution saying that I don't
know anything so my Q Stars can come
from from anywhere so now what do I do
and one way of solving this problem is
to say that given my current knowledge
about the
parameters given my current knowledge
about the parameters which arm should I
play okay so that I my reward is
optimized that's one way of thinking
about it so what should I do then I
should take each Bandit
combination right I should I should say
that okay okay the probability of I me
so Q star one is some value say3 Q star
two is. five Q star three is something
else 1.2 like that so I had to make one
banded problem and then figure out okay
what is the best ter to play here and
then take another banded problem figure
out what is the best ter to play take
another Bandit problem figure out what
is the best arm to play and for each of
these Bandit problems I should look at
what is the probability that this is the
True Q
Stars according to my current knowledge
about the problem so if I start with a
uniform distribution then everything is
equally likely right so all arms I mean
can be optimal all arms can be
non-optimal and so on so forth so I
basically how to play at
random right but it turns out that doing
this computation can be very very
cumbersome you can just think about it
right I'm I'm asking you to figure out
for each arm combination what is the
probability that the arm combination can
occur right and depending on the nature
of the probability distributions you're
assuming this comp computation can
become very very
complex right so the posterior sampling
idea is a way of approximating this
computation so what I do is the
following it's very very simple okay I
have some distribution over what my qar
values will be I have some distribution
over my qar values so what I do is I
draw a sample from the
distribution right so let us say
something like this so my uh
right so qar one I'm saying it's
something like this right and
then that's qar
two plus qar
three you have another color okay okay
good for arms because I'm running out of
colors right so qar 1 2 3 4 right this
is the current distribution I have so
I'm I'm assuming that the true value of
qar Lies somewhere in this range right
and it's most probably this value but I
don't know yet right there's some
uncertainty about what the values are
now what I do is I draw samples you
remember we talked about drawing samples
from goian and other distribution I draw
samples so I draw a
so
basically right
so this is basically my
reward this is my reward axis and this
are a probability axis I draw a sample
for that is
one that is
another that is
another okay so now I have a specific
Bandit
problem where my qar one is this qar 2
is this Q star three is this and qar 4
is this so I've taken this
distribution right and I have drawn one
banded problem from this
distribution okay now I solve this
problem
the right I basically pull arm
three because arm 3 gives me the gave me
the best value here so I pull arm three
now I look at the actual reward I get
for
arm3 right so I pull arm three and let's
say that my arm three reward
is that this is the actual reward that I
get for arm three and now I go back and
update this pH based on this
reward right so what what do you think
it should
be it will become narrower because this
is I kind of read en forcing my original
belief that this is the most probable
outcome
so
yeah this will become my belief now this
is my new distribution now again I try
to sample so the probability that I will
sample a high value for the green arm
goes down now because I when I played
the Green arm I got a smaller value so I
keep doing this until my probability is
kind of converge to the True Q Stars at
the time when a sample problem from that
I'll most probably be sampling the true
problem right the actual problem
underlying that which I'm trying to
solve this is called Thompson sampling
or posterior
sampling so this is getting a lot of uh
attention recently mainly because people
have been able to show that uh this can
give you better regret bounds than
UCB right so this can give you better
regret bounds than UCB and therefore
there's a lot of attention that's being
paid to uh Thompson sampling approaches
uh the analysis gets really hay and in
fact until recently there was no
analysis of the Thompson sampling
approach uh but more recently there have
been several papers in the last 3 4
years there have been several papers uh
that uh that have come up with new
techniques for analyzing uh these kinds
of algorithms different from what we
have been talking about so far are there
round this
th it's kind of round based
right only us one looking at each time
is yeah we're not eliminating any arms
that's what you're saying right well it
turns out that you don't have to even
without eliminating arms you getting
very good complexity and typically what
happens is after some time the
posteriors become so focused right so
the probability of you actually
selecting the bad arm is gone I mean you
don't really need to do a round based uh
uh computation there but yeah I mean
that might be a after few steps room for
sorry after few steps that after few
steps that can be done El yeah I mean
yeah that's the possibility so the only
thing is the only tricky part is once
you do this kind of elimination you have
to come back and analyze it so you saw
how tricky this became right I mean I
gave you the right events to consider
here right but to come up with these
events is a tricky part right so once
you come up with this events it's easy
to bound the probabilities right how do
you know that this is the actual set of
conditions that you should consider
right for you to prove the result so
that is the tricky path now once I say
that okay here is a a round based uh
Thompson sampling approach
then uh going and showing that it
actually gives you the guarantees that
you want becomes tricky I mean people
just the plain Thompson sampling without
any round basing itself resisted
analysis for about a
decade right uh and so so it's not not
immediately clear but there's more
interesting results that have come in uh
yeah so people uh I mean there is a very
old uh style uh algorithm very old class
of algorithms for solving Bandit
problems called learning automat
algorithm these are the people know
about finite State machines right all of
you know about finite State machines
that they have a bunch of states and you
have some input signal symbols coming
and then you jump around the states and
so on so forth right uh so there is a a
class of finite State machines called
variable structured finite State
machines variable structured automator
right and people have used variable
structured automator to solve bandaid
problems I'm not going to get into the
details of it right so it's uh and uh it
turns out that uh some of what the
variable structure automate algorithms
are doing is posterior
sampling right it turns out to be very
similar to posterior sampling and very
recently and and earlier we knew results
only for asymptotic convergence of this
uh learning automated algorithms so very
recently like late last year October or
November of last year uh people have
shown that uh they also satisfy regret
bounds they they satisfy the the log t
uh regret Bond so that mean so a lot of
interesting work that's happening in
this space and uh yeah I mean of course
you're welcome to try a round based
Thomson sampling algorithm I don't know
or just check on RK right the rate at
which work comes out in this space there
might be something already out there
okay so stop here uh the next class we
will look at uh ways of solving the
Bandit problem which do not depend on
the do not depend on estimating the
value function so everything we have
looked on so far look finds the function
Q right capital Q so next class we look
at one class of algorithms which don't
look at uh maintaining the value
function and directly try to learn uh uh
the probabilities which which you have
to select the arms okay
[Applause]